<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><Search><pages Count="53"><page Index="1"><![CDATA[Government of Maharashtra
                            Success Stories





                                                      of
        Menstrual Hygiene Management in Maharashtra




                                     Celebrating MH Week 2021 with

          State Council of Educational Research and Training, Maharashtra

                                               and partners of
                             Maharashtra Urban WASH-ES Coalition]]></page><page Index="2"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra







                     Partners























          Government of Maharashtra


          UNICEF Maharashtra

          Regional Centre for Urban and Environmental Studies of All India Institute of

              Local Self Government, Mumbai

          Citizens Association for Child Rights, Mumbai

          RedIsTheNewGreen(RINGSustainableDevelopmentFoundation), Mumbai





          As part of

          Maharashtra Urban WASH and Environmental Sanitation Coalition–

          A joint initiative by UNICEF Maharashtra and RCUES of AIILSG Mumbai]]></page><page Index="3"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra





                                                                                        Table of

                                                                                        Content








               1)  Breaking the stigma through community participation and access to Menstrual Hygiene
                   facilities.
                   District : Sindhudurg

               2)  Creating a dialogue through strategic planning and participatory approach for MHM.
                   District : Ratnagiri

               3)  Initiative by male teachers to create awareness on menstruation.
                   District : Kolhapur


               4)  Access to sanitation facilities in schools through MHM friendly toilets.
                   District : Aurangabad


               5)  Art and Literature to spread awareness among tribals about MHM.
                   District : Dhule


               6)  Reaching out to flood victims and adolescent girls to create awareness about MHM.
                   District : Sangli

               7)  Red Dot: a two-act play and live session on Facebook to create awareness about MHM.
                   District : Sangli

               8)  Mother – daughter together creating awareness  about MHM.
                   District : Pune

               9)  Puppetry for differently abled students & convergence of organizations for MHM
                   awareness.
                   District : Amravati

               10) MHM sessions in Juvenile home for awareness among detained girls
                   District : Ratnagiri

               11) Awareness on All India Radio about MHM, belief and disbelief
                   District : Dhule


               12) Awareness sessions on MHM across Maharashtra
                   District : All districts of Maharashtra]]></page><page Index="4"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra









                                               Keynote

















         Menstruation is one of the many changes experienced by adolescent girls during the growth years. But
         even today, the attitude towards menstruation, superstitions, and misconceptions about it are causing
         many problems for girls to live a comfortable life.

         For a healthy and happy life, it is necessary to guide the girls about menstrual hygiene management so
         that diet, healthy habits as well as physical and mental needs are taken care of by the family and society.
         Lack of complete knowledge on this subject is affecting the health of girls, their daily life as well as
         school attendance. It is very important to create awareness about this issue. For this, training sessions
         and workshops were conducted in 2019 for all the districts in the state with the help of UNICEF,
         Maharashtra. Since then, the initiatives taken in several schools, have been remarkable and inspiring.


         On the occasion of Menstrual Hygiene week, the ongoing work in the State of Maharashtra is presented
         through this booklet. It is believed that this book will be inspirational in strengthening menstrual hygiene
         management in schools and remote areas of Maharashtra. Congratulations to Maharashtra Urban WASH
         and Environmental Sanitation Coalition (MAHA-UWES-C) at Regional Centre for Urban and Environmental
         Studies of All India Institute of Local Self-Government, Mumbai, UNICEF, Maharashtra, and all master
         trainers across Maharashtra for the ongoing efforts to bring in behavioural change regarding menstrual
         hygiene management.


                                                                           Ms. Vandana Krishna (I.A.S.)
              Additional Chief Secretary, School Education and Sports Department under Government of Maharashtra



























                        I]]></page><page Index="5"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra









                                               Preface

















         Menstruation is a natural process that starts with gradual physical changes in a girl during adolescence.
         However, there exists a misconception in society about menstruation due to a lack of scientific
         knowledge as well as hesitation and shame in speaking about this subject openly; leading to far-reaching
         adverse effects on the future of girls.

         Social awareness is one of the key tools to overcome the alarming situation of menstrual hygiene
         management. The booklet, published jointly by the Department of School Education and Sports, State
         Council for Educational Research and Training, Maharashtra, with UNICEF, Maharashtra, and other
         organizations, outlines the ongoing menstrual hygiene management work across the state.

         The success stories in this booklet will be an inspiration to all master trainers for taking up innovative
         initiatives for MHM awareness. Such initiatives will ensure a bright future for the girls. Congratulations to
         all the contributors who worked for the creation of this booklet.





                                                                              Mr. Vishal Solanki (I.A.S.)
                                                             Commissioner (Education), Pune, Maharashtra
































                                                                                     II]]></page><page Index="6"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra









                                             Foreword

















         Menstruation is one of the important aspect of puberty in girls. The fact that regular menstrual cycles is a
         sign of healthy women is undermined by the societal myths and taboos. In many parts of Maharashtra
         menstruators are restricted from entering holy places, school and sometimes house as well. Disbelief
         and superstitions about menstruation and menstruators, and a lack of awareness about menstrual
         hygiene management has taken a toll on health of many young adolescent girls of Maharashtra.


         The Menstrual Hygiene Day is celebrated worldwide on 28th May every year to break taboos surrounding
         menstruation and raise awareness about good menstrual hygiene management practices. In the
         Menstrual Hygiene Week 2021, UNICEF, Maharashtra with Department of Education and Sports under
         Government of Maharashtra, and its partner organizations had undertaken multiple activities. The week
         long activities focused on menstruation and eradicating period stigma by creating a dialogue with multiple
         stakeholders working in urban  sector. The activities also covered documenting good practices
         undertaken in Maharashtra, creating awareness across community members through local level
         engagement,social media,and print media.

         The State Council of Educational Research and Training (SCERT), Department of Education and Sports,
         Government of Maharashtra along with UNICEF, Maharashtra have been contributing towards educating
         men and women across Maharashtra to break the stigma. The main aim of awareness campaigns is to
         develop scientific understanding and create dialogue in the society about menstruation. In Maharashtra,
         awareness campaigns are conducted by identified master trainers from schools in each district. The
         sessions conducted involve discussion and guidance on various aspects of menstruation like physical
         and mental health during periods, diet for adolescent girls, good habits during menstruation, and
         menstrual hygiene management.

         Through this book I congratulate all master trainers and volunteers that are helping and guiding
         menstruators to live happy and healthy life. I would also like to acknowledge the team of UNICEF,
         Maharashtra, Department of Education and Sports under Government of Maharashtra and Maharashtra
         Urban WASH and Environmental Sanitation Coalition (MAHA-UWES-C) at Regional Centre for Urban and
         Environmental Studies of All India Institute of Local Self-Government, Mumbai, in compilation of this
         book. Their efforts shall help open up a dialogue and build a healthy atmosphere for menstruators.
                                                                           Ms. Rajeshwari Chandrasekar
                                                                 Chief of Field Office, UNICEF, Maharashtra








                        III]]></page><page Index="7"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra









                                               Message

















         Good health and education are important aspects of an enduring lifestyle. Changes experienced during
         the growth years in adolescents have a significant impact on their mental health. Puberty in girls begins
         earlier than the physical changes are visible. Menstruation is one of the major changes experienced by
         girls during puberty. Early education through discussions and conversations about puberty can help the
         girls accept these changes effortlessly.


         Academic institutions are of prime importance to bring in this education as well as social awareness.
         Department of Education and Sports under Government of Maharashtra (GoM) has thus welcomed the
         celebration of Menstrual Hygiene week thereby initiating a dialogue and acknowledging efforts already
         undertaken in the state to bring in social change. Awareness campaigns on menstruation and menstrual
         hygiene management are conducted in primary schools and tribal areas of Maharashtra with the joint
         effort of Department of Education and Sports under GoM and UNICEF, Maharashtra.

         Educating adolescents and their parents about the biological process of menstruation, use of sanitary
         products, ‘Do’s and Don’ts’ for a healthy life and parent’s role in providing healthy living and support to
         their child has helped improve overall health of women. This book highlights innovative ways adopted by
         master trainers to overcome hurdles faced in different geographical and social settings of Maharashtra
         while conducting awareness campaigns.

         As an applaud to their contribution in improving menstrual hygiene, Department of Education and Sports
         under GoM with UNICEF Maharashtra and Maharashtra Urban WASH and Environmental Sanitation
         Coalition (MAHA-UWES-C) at Regional Centre for Urban and Environmental Studies of All India Institute
         of Local Self-Government, Mumbai have recognized noteworthy success stories in menstrual hygiene
         management. These success stories shall inspire people to break the stigma and build a better world for
         menstruators to live in.


                                                                                    Dr. Dinakar Temkar
                             Director, School Education and Sports Department under Government of Maharashtra
















                                                                                     IV]]></page><page Index="8"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra









                                              Message

















          The physical and mental changes experienced by adolescent boys and girls are often discussed, unlike
          menstruation. The stigma around menstruation has led to unjust practices at school, community places,
          holy places as well as home. A girl seeks sensible companions to cope up with the emotional turmoil
          experienced during menstruation. This situation can definitely improve if school girls are equipped with
          scientific knowledge and appropriate support.


          In 2019, the Equity Department under the State Council for Educational Research and Training in
          collaboration with UNICEF, Maharashtra undertook training sessions for 5 teachers from each district on
          menstrual hygiene management. This program was further extended to all other teachers and girls in the
          district. Awareness sessions were conducted remotely even during COVID – 19 pandemic. The
          cooperation of the principals of all the District Institutes for Education and Training (DIET) in this work is
          particularly noteworthy.

          The success stories of contributions by teachers in the state regarding menstrual hygiene management
          are compiled in this book. Inspired by these stories, the main objective is to make efforts at all levels of
          society to effectively spread the subject to all girls. We are delighted to bring this book to you in
          collaboration with UNICEF, Maharashtra and other organizations.



                                                                                 Dr. Kamaladevi Awate,
                                                                     Deputy Director, Department of Equity,
                                      at State Council for Educational Research and Training, Pune, Maharashtra


























                        V]]></page><page Index="9"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra









                                   Acknowledgement

















          Menstruation is a natural biological function experienced by half of the population, yet it is still often
          stigmatized in our society today. Lack of importance towards menstrual hygiene not only affects the
          physical health of menstruators but also has grave impact on their mental health. Lack of awareness and
          facilities has also accelerated school dropout rates of girls reaching puberty, undermining their ability to
          grow as individuals.


          Schools are crucial and play a key role in social awareness and behavioral change. Over the past decade,
          various efforts have been undertaken in menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra through State
          Departments and valuable contribution of non-profit organizations led by UNICEF, Maharashtra. These
          systematic and persistent efforts in bringing in awareness through various platforms and strategically
          designed programs has helped broaden the horizon for menstrual hygiene and related topics in the state.


          As a part of World Menstrual Hygiene Day celebrated on 28th May every year, Maharashtra Urban WASH
          and Environmental Sanitation Coalition (MAHA-UWES-C) at Regional Centre for Urban and Environmental
          Studies of All India Institute of Local Self-Government, Mumbai with support from Department of
          Education and Sports, Government of Maharashtra have developed this book on success stories on
          menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra. We would like to acknowledge and appreciate the
          contribution of all the teachers, students and other stakeholders who have shared their efforts in
          spreading awareness and developing good practices on ground.


          I would like to thank State Council of Educational Research and Training, Maharashtra, Department of
          Education and Sports, Government of Maharashtra, UNICEF, Maharashtra Red is the New Green (RING),
          Mumbai and Citizens Association for Child Rights (CACR), Mumbai, for their support in celebration of
          Menstrual Hygiene Week, 2021. I would also like to thank the team at Secretariat Maharashtra Urban
          WASH and Environmental Sanitation Coalition (MAHA-UWES-C) at Regional Centre for Urban and
          Environmental Studies of All India Institute of Local Self-Government, Mumbai who have enthusiastically
          worked towards the compilation of this book. I hope these success stories will be helpful and
          motivational to changemakers on ground in adopting appropriate menstrual hygiene practices and
          establishing important dialogue between men and women, which will further be the cause of women’s
          health and well-being.


                                                                                   Ms.Utkarsha Kavadi
                            Director, Secretariat, Maharashtra Urban WASH and Environmental Sanitation Coalition
                                                                             at RCUES of AIILSG Mumbai





                                                                                     VI]]></page><page Index="10"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra









                                       About the book

















         Menstruation is a natural biological function in the life of every woman. Girls in the age group of 10yrs to
         16yrs undergo many physical and emotional changes which need to be handled in a sensitive manner.
         This important phase in the life of every girl and woman is many times stigmatized. Menstruation and
         menstrual hygiene are often flanked by superstitious belief.

         Efforts are being made at national and state level to eradicate the myths and provide safe access to
         toilets and menstrual hygiene facilities through programs like National Health mission and Swachh
         Bharat Mission. Joint action of Ministry of Women and Child Development, Ministry of Housing and
         Urban Affairs, State Government of Maharashtra and non-government organizations (NGOs) is
         instrumental in achieving people’s participation in awareness campaigns especially in vulnerable areas to
         improve menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra.


         The State Council of Educational Research and Training (SCERT), Department of Education and Sports,
         Government of Maharashtra along with UNICEF Maharashtra and other partner organizations are making
         an effort to improve the condition of menstruating women in urban and rural Maharashtra. Menstrual
         Hygiene Management trainers across Maharashtra have undertaken numerous efforts in menstrual
         hygiene management and have made paramount contribution in changing number of fatalities and
         decrease the rate of school dropouts of adolescent girls due to menstruation.

                                                                 th
         In light of the World Menstrual Hygiene Day celebrated on 28 May of every year, Maharashtra Urban
         WASH and Environmental Sanitation Coalition (MAHA-UWES-C) at Regional Centre for Urban and
         Environmental Studies of All India Institute of Local Self-Government, Mumbai with support from UNICEF,
         Maharashtra and Department of Education and Sports under Government of Maharashtra and partner
         organizations Citizens Association for Child Rights (CACR), Mumbai and Red is the New Green (RING),
         Mumbai have recognized noteworthy success stories of master trainers across Maharashtra.





















                       VII]]></page><page Index="11"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="12"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra





         Breaking the stigma



         through community participation and access to MH facilities















               Z.P. Primary School
               Taluka: Kankavli
               District: Sindhudurg









                 The Initiative

                  The menstrual hygiene management trainers in Nandgav village of Kankanvli adopted an
                  innovative way of celebrating birthdays of adolescent girls in school by gifting sanitary napkins
                  to break the social stigma about menstruation and improve access to menstrual hygiene
                  products. Along with this an initiative to develop changing room was undertaken to improve
                  access to sanitation facilities.



                 What was achieved?

                  Campaigns conducted in schools has helped spread social awareness among people about
                  menstrual hygiene which has led to behavioral change among adolescent girls. Girls have
                  become more confident and reluctance to attend school during menstruation has reduced.
                  Access to good hygiene facilities have helped improve physical as well as mental health.
                  Sindhudurg district has more than 100 changing rooms formed and maintained through public
                  participation.



                 Who contributed?
                  All changing rooms are developed with the help of the principal, teachers and students from 5th-
                  12th standards. Other than that, District Coordinator (girl education) and gram panchayat
                  members have contributed.


         Who were impacted?

          Around 2000 adolescent girls from 5th-12th standards are using these facilities.



                                                                                     2]]></page><page Index="13"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra













         A stigma around "menses" among the municipal school students and teachers lingered in Nandgav village of
         Sindhudurg district. They used to shy away from readily talking about menstruation. But the training
         sessions on Menstrual Hygiene Management (MHM) for teachers encouraged them to speak about the topic
         candidly without any fear or humiliation. This awareness was to be brought among girls and their parents as
         well. Along with ignorance about MHM, lack of facilities and menstrual hygiene products were the major
         barriers to practice what was preached by the MHM trainers of Nandgav villgae.
         To break the barrier among male and female members, teachers decided to celebrate birthdays of
         adolescent girls by gifting them sanitary napkins distinctly by the male teachers and male members of
         family. Even the male village committee members actively participated in the activity. Looking at the
         positive support, initiative to improve sanitation facilities in school was undertaken.

         To improve sanitation facilities in school, idea of changing room was proposed. Initially, it seemed too
         ambitious to propose this in front of the school committee. However, to everyone’s utter surprise, support
         from the higher officials was extended and a letter of invitation was sent to the parents of these students
         and series of parent teacher meetings were conducted. The concept of changing room in schools was thus
         developed and implemented through student teacher and parent participation.

         A changing room was made out of an empty abandoned room or a new room whichever was easily available
         in school. It necessarily had a functional toilet with running water, a washbasin with handwash, a stock of
         sanitary pads, drinking water, a bed with bedsheet, a mirror, towel and detergent powder too. Also, the
         rooms are filled with posters, slogans and images giving messages about the menstrual hygiene
         management practices.
         This in turn has developed confidence among the girls. Innovative way of celebrating birthday has helped
         sensitize male members of society and break the stigma. Due to regular guidance and preaching about
         Menstrual Hygiene Management from the master trainers, the school drop out rate of the adolescent girls
         has reduced remarkably. These rooms have allowed girls to attend school regularly and access better
         services in schools.

                                                                            Smt. Smita Prakash Nalawade
                                          Assistant Program Officer, Samagraha Shiksha Z.P. school, Sindhudurg


























                        3]]></page><page Index="14"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="15"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra




          Creating a dialogue



          through strategic planning and participatory approach for MHM
















               Pachad School No.1

               Taluka: Chiplun
               District:Ratnagiri








                 The Initiative
                  MHM trainers of Pachad village realized that the communication on menstruation and
                  menstrual hygiene management is often one way (only through volunteers). To initiate
                  discussions and break the stigma, an action plan for activities was prepared which involved
                  interactive awareness sessions and activities to ensure active participation from parents as
                  well as students.





                  What was achieved?
                  The initiative has helped create a dialogue among young girls about menstrual hygiene.
                  Commendable behavioral changes can be observed among girls and their parents. Early
                  education to school girls has helped overcome their fear for first period.


                  Who contributed?
                  All teachers from Pachad School No. 1 were the major contributors in conducting awareness
                  sessions and activities among students. Support from principal of Pachad School No. 1 and
                  gram panchayat members was noteworthy. Other than this, active participation of girls from
                  class 5th to 10th and their parents helped implement the program successfully.


         Who were impacted?

          The programs have helped reach adolescent school girls in Pachad and their mothers.





                        5]]></page><page Index="16"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra













         School is the primary institution which can be harnessed to spread social awareness. Department of
         Education and Sports, Government of Maharashtra has been conducting awareness programs on issues
         stigmatized by the society. One such topic is menstruation. MHM trainers from Pachad School number 1
         have been actively conducting awareness sessions in school to educate girls and their parents about
         menstrual hygiene management.

         MHM trainers from this school worked out an action plan to conduct a series of sessions and activities
         through out the year to initiate important discussions. It aimed at involving parents and adolescent girls to
         create a dialogue among them about menstrual hygiene.

         Sessions in the first half of the year were dedicated to educating girls and parents about various aspects of
         menstruation while other sessions were conducted through active participation of girls through activities
         like slogan making and play for parents and male members in school.

         First session was conducted on ‘Parents role in providing healthy living to their girl child’. In this session
         biological information on menstruation and physical changes experienced during puberty were conveyed. In
         the following session parents and girls were informed about Do’s and Don'ts during menstruation, use of
         sanitary products and diet for good health.

         Looking at the popularity of 90s cartoon character Meena and Raju, stories for menstrual hygiene
         management were conceptualized. Since then these stories have been used to educate 10 - 14 age group
         girls and their mothers about good practices in menstruation for healthy life. Meena - Raju characters helped
         build and spread social message among the youth.

         In the interactive sessions parents and students shared their experiences and discussed problems faced
         during menstruation. This helped create dialogue between students and parents. Last three sessions
         comprised of information, education and communication (IEC) activities through girls like poster making,
         slogan preparation and street play. In the final session, an act was performed using these slogans and
         posters by girls to spread awareness among parents and other village members.
         These activities have inculcated awareness among girls like maintaining good hygiene during menstruation,
         recording menstrual cycle and having a healthy diet.
                                                                                 Smt. Sampada Kanekar
                                                      Primary School Teacher, Pachad school no. 1, Ratnagiri
























                                                                                     6]]></page><page Index="17"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="18"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra





         Initiative by male teachers



         to create awareness on menstruation












                Anuskura and

                Karanjaphen

                Taluka: Shahuwadi
                District: Kolhapur








                 The Initiative
                  Schools in Anuskura and Karanjaphen villages of Shahuwadi taluka had no female teachers,
                  which had become a major barrier for menstrual hygiene management awareness programs in
                  tribal villages. Hence, MHM trainers (male teachers) in this village set up a platform in the form
                  of ‘Mazhi Didi’ helpline number, to discuss issues related to menstrual hygiene.






                 What was achieved?

                 Helpline number has become a popular medium for expressing emotional distress and spread
                 awareness among younger girls. Awareness campaigns have helped reduce rate of infections
                 and fatalities due to unhygienic conditions during menstruation among menstruators. Overall it
                 is helping girls to maintain good physical as well as mental health.



                 Who contributed?
                 Along with primary school teachers of all schools in Shahuwadi taluka, contribution of female
                 volunteers from colleges and NGOs was of prime importance. Support from Panchayat samiti
                 of Shahuwadi and Principal of District Education and Skill Development Institute was
                 noteworthy.

         Who were impacted?

         The programs has helped reach adolescent girls and tribal women in Shahuwadi taluka.





                                                                                      8]]></page><page Index="19"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra













          Adolescence is a very important stage in the growth and development of children. At this stage boys as well
          as girls undergo physical and mental changes. During this age, providing health education helps in overall
          development of students; menstrual hygiene management being one of it. Children of these taluka were
          unaware and lacked scientific knowledge about biological changes experienced by girls during their puberty.
          The southern part of Shahuwadi taluka in Kolhapur district is rural. Also there are no female teachers in any
          primary schools of Anuskura and Karanjaphen to guide and help adolescent girls during their first period or
          discuss concerns related to menstruation. Girls are also quite reluctant to discuss concerns regarding
          menstruation with male teachers in the school.
          To address this issue MHM trainers (male) in primary schools of Anuskura and Karanjaphen started an
          awareness campaign named ‘Kali Khulatana’ in schools and tribal areas of these villages. Through this
          program, women are educated about the importance of menstrual hygiene, use of sanitary products and Dos
          and Don'ts during periods. Earlier, menstruation was considered as ‘problem’ as myths and unhygienic
          practices during menstruation led to severe infections among girls. Eradicating myths surrounding
          menstruation was one of the key objective of this program.
          Since there are no female teachers in any primary school in these villages, a helpline number was set up
          with the help of NGOs and volunteers from colleges. ‘Mazhi Didi’ helpline number helped adolescent girls
          discuss concerns during their first periods and related health issues. Female volunteers from colleges
          addressed these calls. ‘Mazhi Didi’ helpline number has become a strong medium for expression during
          menstruation. The helpline number serves as an important platform to help girls improve mental as well as
          physical health and eradicate myths about menstruation.




                                                                            Shri. Anil Pandurang Kamble
                                                           Teacher, Vidya Mandir Kante, Shahuwadi, Kolhapur



































                        9]]></page><page Index="20"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="21"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra





         Access to sanitation



         facilities in schools through MHM friendly toilets















                Z. P. School

                Taluka: Ladsavangi
                District: Aurangabad








                  The Initiative
                  School drop outs and low attendance in classes has been a major concern for girl students in
                  Z. P. School, Ladsavangi. Taking this into consideration, efforts were undertaken by teachers in
                  developing MHM friendly toilets and educating girls about menstrual hygiene management.






                  What was achieved?
                  Changing rooms are helping menstruators maintain hygiene and take short breaks from long
                  school hours instead of taking a leave. Vending machines provide access to sanitary pads at
                  minimal rate. Students have made red dot paper hanger and red dot dustbin for disposal of
                  sanitary napkins. Awareness sessions by gynecologists have created an impact on girls. Due to
                  this girls have become diligent towards recording menstrual cycle, hand washing and proper
                  disposal of used sanitary pads.


                 Who contributed?

                 Awareness and changing room initiative involved participation from students, teachers,
                 headmaster, parents and villagers. Gram panchayat provided financial support and manpower
                 for developing changing room and facilities there in. The vending machines and napkins are
                 financed by the Loopin Foundation.


         Who were impacted?
          The initiative has helped around 200 girls in Zilla Parishad School of Ladsavangi.




                       11]]></page><page Index="22"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra











          Taboo around menstruation hampers initiation of a critical dialogue. It thus prevents development of
          essential infrastructure necessary for young girls to have a hygienic period. A small impetus on building
          menstruation friendly facilities allows girls learn healthy practices around menstruation.

          School drop outs and low attendance in classes has been a major concern for girl students in Z. P. School,
          Ladsavangi. They lacked access to safe menstruation facilities like toilets, sanitary napkins and other
          hygiene products. Taking this into consideration, efforts were undertaken by teachers in developing
          menstruation friendly toilets and educating girls about menstrual hygiene.
          Realizing the need for menstrual hygiene management facilities to improve attendance of girls, teachers
          have undertaken the initiative to create changing rooms which were equipped with functional toilets, running
          water, a washbasin with handwash and a stock of sanitary napkins. The rooms also have drinking water, a
          bed, a mirror, towel and detergent powder. This has helped girls sustain the long school hours during
          periods and improved their attendance.

          Along with provision of facilities, educating girls and addressing the curiosities of both boys and girls about
          menstruation was thought to be necessary. For this awareness sessions under the guidance of subject
          experts and gynecologists are conducted.
          Surveys were also conducted among students during these awareness sessions which showed that most
          girls were unaware about puberty, the biological reasons for menses. They lacked knowledge on use of
          sanitary napkins, disposal techniques and use of incinerators.
          Understanding the problem of sanitary waste disposal in rural areas and methods of sanitary waste
          management were also discussed. Covers for soiled sanitary pads with red dot, separate dustbins and
          incinerators are installed to facilitate onsite disposal of menstrual waste.

                                                                                       Smt. Sarika Jain
                                               Secondary School Teacher, Z. P. School Ladsavangi, Aurangabad




































                                                                                     12]]></page><page Index="23"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="24"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra





          Art and Literature



          to spread awareness among tribals about MHM















                Bhoicha Pada

                Taluka: Sakri
                District: Dhule








                   The Initiative
                   Bhoicha Pada is a tribal village in Sakri taluka. Lack of education and illiteracy created a
                   communication gap between the Z.P. teachers of Sakri taluka and villagers. The gap was
                   bridged through poems and rangoli exhibitions that depicted biological process of
                   menstruation and menstrual hygiene management practices. A compilation of these poems
                   was published through ‘Udita’.



                   What was achieved?
                   Poems and art works helped in delivering the message to uneducated tribal women and girls.
                   ‘Udita’ served as a platform for the MHM trainers to express and spread awareness about
                   menstrual hygiene in an innovative way. Rangolis served as best visual medium to
                   communicate with the tribal women. Decrease in cases of infection and health issues due to
                   unhygienic conditions among menstruators are recorded. Art and literature helped create a
                   dialogue among tribals about menstruation.


                   Who contributed?
                   To complete the book and conduct rangoli exhibition, teachers from Z.P. schools in Sakri
                   Dr.Shobha Khandare, Dr.Prabhakar Kshirsagar were instrumental. Smt. Aparna Kulkarni-
                   Gowande from UNICEF, Maharashtra encouraged throughout. Support from the District
                   Instituite of Education and Training (DIET) organization and female teachers of Dhule was
                   noteworthy.

         Who were impacted?

          Villagers and school going adolescent girls in Sakri taluka are benefited from  this initiative.


                                                                                     14]]></page><page Index="25"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra












         Our ancestors strongly believed that during menstruation a woman endeavors immense alterations in
         mental, physical and emotional health. In following years this believe was encompassed by myths and
         superstitions. Prevailing illiteracy tabooed menstruation and menstruators and termed impure.

         Similar situation was experienced in Bhoicha Pada village of Sakri taluka in Dhule district. Disbelief and
         superstitions about menstruation and menstruators in the society was taking toll on health of the
         menstruators.

         Due to inadequate exposure to education facility among the tribals of Bhoicha Pada village, the approach
         towards spreading awareness in terms of menstruation had to be different. The communication gap was
         bridged by using art and literature for awareness. With the help of teachers and principals of schools, an
         anthology of poems and verses was published. Using these verses and poems, awareness campaigns were
         conducted to burst the myths and taboos related to menstrual hygiene and menstruation. Poems and
         verses were compiled in a book ‘Udita’. It serves as a medium to educate girls in schools of Sakri taluka and
         platform to the changemakers and menstruators.
         To burst the myths and taboos surrounding menstrual hygiene, Rangoli exhibitions on menstrual hygiene at
         social gathering places were organized to spread awareness among tribals. Rangolis acted as an visual aid
         to the tribals to understand importance of menstruation and sensitize about the topic. Rangolis depicted
         biological changes that a girl undergoes during this phase, use of sanitary products and precautions to be
         taken to maintain good hygiene and avoid infection.

                                                                  Smt. Hemlata Yashwant Patil - Bhamare
                                                            Primary School Teacher, Z.P. School Sakri, Dhule








































                       15]]></page><page Index="26"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="27"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra






          Reaching out to flood victims


          and adolescent girls to create awareness about MHM















                Damani High School

                Taluka: Sangli
                District :Sangli








                 The Initiative
                  Due to extreme floods in Sangli district in 2019, flood victims were provided temporary shelter
                  in Damani High School. These temporary shelter lacked facilities for menstruating women. The
                  Menstrual Hygiene Management Master trainers reached out to the flood victims to spread
                  awareness among them. Thereafter they conducted menstrual hygiene management sessions
                  for students of municipal schools across the district.



                 What was achieved?

                 It is indisputable that the campaigns conducted by the master trainers are not only successful
                 in creating awareness among the adolescent girls and school officials but is creating a positive
                 impact on the women of the society. In addition to this, the trainers also received numerous
                 calls from these women narrating about their health. The trainers were successfully able to
                 create a wave of awareness among these women even in difficult times.



                 Who contributed?

                 There was active participation from district municipal school teachers, students, parents and
                 community members.


         Who were impacted?

          50 flood victim women of the Sangli district and 65 adolescent girls from the municipal school were
          present for the awareness session and were directly benefitted from the initiatives the school had taken
          in response to the training sessions of the Menstrual Hygiene Management.



                       17]]></page><page Index="28"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra















          The first menstrual hygiene management training was given in August 2017 all over Maharashtra. Smt.
          Aparna Kulkarni-Gowande, State Communication Consultant for Water, Sanitation and Menstrual Hygiene,
          UNICEF, Maharashtra imparted scientific knowledge about menstrual cycle. After these training sessions,
          Sangli district experienced heavy flooding in 2020. Many families along the river took shelter in different
          schools. Most of these women lived in Damani High School where food and shelter was provided. Smt.
          Sudha Patil- Menstrual Hygiene Management master trainer reached out to approximately 150 women and
          imparted awareness about menstrual hygiene management.

          When the flood water receded and the women went to their respective houses, menstrual hygiene
          management trainers started receiving calls from these flood victimized women about health and
          menstruation. In fact, at that time, even when their lives were not completely stable as the villages did not
          have continuous electricity and water supply women wanted to know how to take care of their health and
          follow safe hygiene practices during menstruation. There was contentment among the trainers to witness
          the awareness about the menstrual health among those women and left no stone unturned in guiding them.
          Trainings were further conducted at the district and the taluka level. Post these trainings, again menstrual
          hygiene management sessions started in schools. It was evident that the work of awareness about
          menstrual hygiene management was bringing about a positive impact. Many initiatives about MHM were
          undertaken due to the awareness brought in by the trainings such as pad banks came into schools, separate
          ‘changing rooms’ were arranged, the vending machines were installed and girls began to openly discuss
          about menstruation. Predominantly, school dropouts had reduced. Overall, there was acceptance from
          school and society.



                                                                               Smt. Shanta Tamma Vader
                                                           Assistant Teacher, Patwardhan High School Sangli

































                                                                                     18]]></page><page Index="29"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="30"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra





         Red dot - a two act play



         and live session on Facebook to create awareness about MHM













                Sangli Municipal
                Corporation

                Taluka: Sangli
                District: Sangli








                 The Initiative
                 A two act play on menstrual hygiene management was scripted by one of the MHM master
                 trainer. Various topics like why and how does menstruation occur, importance of cleanliness
                 during menstruation, diet, beliefs and superstitions are all painted in the story in such a way that
                 it is easy to understand and leave an impact on the spectator. Further a Facebook live session
                 "Lockdown and women's menstrual cycle" was conducted by the master trainer to reach out to
                 a larger population.





                 What was achieved?
                 The play stood as an effective medium to spread awareness among the students. Social media
                 served as an important platform in spreading awareness across a huge number of women with
                 different backgrounds across different regions.


                 Who contributed?
                 The play had 9 teachers from government and private schools, 5 school students and 3 college
                 students who performed at different locations with support of the district organizing team.


          Who were impacted?
          Nearly 1000 spectators were present to watch this play. It has reached out to 1500 viewers on Facebook
          and many others through YouTube too.






                                                                                     20]]></page><page Index="31"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra















          In the story of the two act play "Red Dot", Doctor Divya, who has worked with UNICEF, Maharashtra is raising
          awareness in her village. She is opposed by her mother-in-law to work in this awareness program. But other
          members in the house support her to carry out her duties. She is assisted in this task by the village
          promoter and the village sarpanch. This play is based on an original story. It is a journey from the
          awakening of a family to the awakening of a village. Red Dot, a two-act play, was performed at Bhave
          Natyagriha Sangli.

          On 4th December 2019, all the teachers and actors performed in the State level Drama Competition. The
          practice of the play began about five months earlier. It had a total of seventeen artists. The play received
          overwhelming positive response from the viewers. After facing many problems like getting actors for the
          play, financial planning, space for rehearsals, the play "Red Dot" was presented in the state drama
          competition.
          The play was well-received as an important subject. Nearly 1000 spectators were present to watch this play.
          It is also available on the YouTube channel garnering positive responses.
          Another Facebook live program "Lockdown and women's menstrual cycle" was conducted through the
          Facebook group Apala Manasashastra during the pandemic lockdown period. This also received a good
          response with 1500 viewers. The session was later uploaded on YouTube and thus reached out to the
          viewers who missed out on the live session.



                                                                              Smt. Sudha Rajendra Patil
                                                                    Subject Assistant - English, DIET Sangli







































                       21]]></page><page Index="32"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="33"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra





          Mother-daughter



          together creating awareness about MHM















                Daund urban & rural

                Taluka: Daund
                District: Pune








                 The Initiative
                 A series of seminars and webinars were conducted for masses by the MHM master trainer with
                 assistance of her daughter. The awareness sessions on menstrual hygiene management aimed
                 to curb the disbelief around menstruation and social practices like isolating during
                 menstruation due to which girls have to miss many days of school or even drop out from
                 school.





                 What was achieved?
                 The students confidently talk about menstruation and receive support from school
                 management committee with respect to this topic. The most effective thing is that in this
                 training, a new cadre of young students are getting ready to spread awareness about menstrual
                 hygiene management.


                 Who contributed?
                 There was immense support from all the officials of the DIET Department. Further, guidance
                 from Smt. Aparna Kulkarni-Gowande from UNICEF, Maharashtra gave a direction to the master
                 trainer to create awareness about MHM on a large scale.


         Who were impacted?

         Approximately 20,000 students from rural and urban areas of Maharashtra and around 10,000 labour,
         parents and Asha workers from remote areas were impacted.




                       23]]></page><page Index="34"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra















          Girls coming from far away places would remain absent due to menstruation. Also, when their mothers
          would menstruate, daughters would have to cook and thus would come late to school. In 2014, after
          discussing with the girls, it was seen that women and girls were living separately outside the barn during the
          menstrual period. In discussion with mothers about stopping this ritual, they feared God's wrath upon them,
          the fear that something bad would happen in our house and many other superstitions.


          Department of Education and Sports under Government of Maharashtra and UNICEF, Maharashtra conducted
          training for menstrual hygiene management in 2019, which built confidence to advocate strongly for
          menstrual hygiene and bursting myths & disbelief. School sessions on MHM were carried out in all schools
          of Daund block. After lockdown, offline sessions were discontinued. There was an invitation to lecture for an
          online MHM session due to the pandemic. It was then noticed that four hundred students and teachers are
          sitting in their classrooms and training properly through laptops and speakers. The success of this program
          gave inspiration to the mother and the daughter who was helping her in managing technicalities of online
          platform.


          After this Ms. Sakshi Katam, daughter of Smt. Sunita Katam accompanied her mother to impart information
          about Menstrual Hygiene Management through the school program. The importance of this work was
          realized once again by the MHM master trainer- Ms Sunita Katam and she decided to undertake their work
          on creating awareness on menstruation by conducting online trainings for the school students of the taluka.


          With the support from various NGOs, clubs, SHGs and other frontline workers, they reached out to the
          talukas. Here, Ms. Sakshi Katam assisted in training program by handling technical matters. Creating a link,
          sending it to the teacher, taking the program on time, soliciting children's feedback, and many other things
          where handled by her, while her mother was undertaking awareness sessions. They successfully completed
          the online training of a thousand students. Based on the feedback from previous trainings they planned the
          next trainings. For this they collected feedbacks on Google form from the participants after every training.
          This activity started from 5th September 2014 and is ongoing now too.
                                                                                 Smt. Sunita Vijay Katam
                                                                        Post Graduate Teacher,Yavat, Pune


























                                                                                     24]]></page><page Index="35"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="36"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra






          Puppetry



          for differently abled students and convergence of organisations for MHM awareness











               DIET Amravati

               Taluka: Amravati

               District: Amravati










                 The Initiative
                  Creating awareness about menstrual hygiene management amongst the differently abled
                  students in an effective and friendly way is crucial. Hence ‘puppetry’ was used as a medium to
                  create awareness. Also, with the increase in the number of dropouts of the adolescent girls
                  from school, there was a need to address the misconceptions related to menstruation
                  management.



                 What was achieved?

                 Menstruation is no more a topic to be stigmatized, rather it has become a topic of discussion in
                 Amravati. Media coverage for the menstrual hygiene management has helped in reaching out to
                 a larger population. Women officials like the doctors, police, media, govt. servants like railway
                 officials etc. participated enthusiastically which marked a new beginning. .


                 Who contributed?

                 There was immense cooperation from diverse organizations like the District Education and
                 Training Institute, JCI Amravati Golden, JCIRAT WING, Kaivalya Foundation, Sir Foundation
                 Amravati, District Gynecology and Obstetrics Association Amravati and UNICEF, Maharashtra.


         Who were impacted?

          Awareness about Menstrual Hygiene Management was spread among 95,641 students and parents at
          district level




                                                                                     26]]></page><page Index="37"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra















         It was realized by the MHM master trainer through her numerous field visits that there was a need to create
         awareness among the differently abled girls. Thus, on the World Puppetry Day - 21st March, puppetry was
         used as a medium by the trainer to guide differently abled students about menstrual hygiene management.
         Through the puppet show named “Chinki’s world” they took up a sensitive subject of Menstrual Hygiene and
         created awareness among masses. More than 375 students were present for the event. The session was
         followed by healthy discussions among the teachers, students and parents. The event received appreciation
         from district level officials.

         To create an impact on a larger population, the Menstrual Hygiene Management trainers of Amaravati
         district came together and undertook the responsibility of imparting menstrual hygiene management training
         to 95,641 students at the district level. This was carried out with the convergence of various organizations
         which have jointly arranged several workshops on menstrual hygiene management. Various experts too
         guided the audience on the topic of diet and hygiene during menstruation. Respected women from all fields
         came up to join hands in creating awareness among the community.




                                                                          Smt. Dipali Dilip Bhabulkar
                                                                 Subject Assistant - Marathi, DIET Amravati












































                       27]]></page><page Index="38"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="39"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra






          MHM sessions in Juvenile home



          For awareness among detained girls











               Ratnagiri Municipal

               Corporation

               Taluka: Ratnagiri
               District: Ratnagiri








                 The Initiative
                  Among many facilities that are provided to the youth at detention centers, education is seen as
                  a cornerstone for youth rehabilitation. A large percentage of incarcerated juveniles are
                  identified as children with special needs. The Equity Department under SCERT, Pune had
                  organized a 7-day educational session, during which a series of MHM awareness sessions were
                  conducted for the girls in all the juvenile correctional facilities across the Ratnagiri district.



                 What was achieved?

                 The victimized girls hesitated to express themselves due to their past events. MHM sessions
                 helped girls to open up and share their experiences of menstruation. They have started
                 discussing concerns among themselves and in turn feel empowered. This has led to overall
                 positive behavioral change among the girls


                 Who contributed?

                 The sessions were organized by the Equity Department of State Council and Educational
                 Research and Training (SCERT), Pune. It was implemented by resource person Ms. Ashwini
                 Kane under the guidance of officers and Principal of DIET, Ratnagiri.


         Who were impacted?

          Sessions of MHM awareness were conducted for the girls in all the juvenile centers, across the district
          Ratnagiri.




                       29]]></page><page Index="40"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra















         A letter was issued by the Equity Department of SCERT, Pune to conduct a special 7-day session for the girls
         in the juvenile detention centers. This was arranged so that they were not deprived of mainstream
         education. The sessions included life skills development, career guidance, scholarship exam guidance,
         various online learning streams, and most importantly, the MHM awareness sessions. This initiative was
         implemented in all the juvenile centers across the district Ratnagiri. The implementation was carried out by
         resource persons, under the guidance of Dr. Patil and all the officers from DIET, Ratnagiri. The zero-
         tolerance policies seemed to be more strict in juvenile centers than any other traditional schools.
         Since juvenile detention centers operate on the foundation of rehabilitating the youths, different mental
         health programs were provided for their help. Life skills lessons were first imparted to the trainers as these
         girls required special counseling to live a healthy and self-reliant life. A background study was done with the
         help of their caretaker before they commenced the sessions. There was a long-standing connection found
         between girls who committed crimes and their mental health concerns. There were some homeless girls,
         many were victims while some were criminals. Therefore, it was very difficult for them to grasp life skills. In
         the training sessions, special emphasis was given on MHM, motherhood, pregnancy, mental changes,
         attraction, good touch and, bad touch, etc.

         A film by UNICEF, on “Your body is your right” was shown to them which too was very insightful. There was a
         visible positive change observed by the caretaker for MHM among these girls. One of the elder girls took the
         responsibility of Peer leader for help related to MHM. These sessions are necessary and should be
         continued regularly.
                                                                                 Smt. Ashwini Kane
                                                                 Subject Assistant - Marathi, DIET Ratnagiri






































                                                                                     30]]></page><page Index="41"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="42"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra






          Awareness on All India Radio



          about MHM, belief and disbelief











               Dhule Municipal

               Corporation

               Taluka: Dhule
               District: Dhule








                 The Initiative
                  Many religions have menstruation-related traditions. It was seen in Dhule that menstruating
                  women are traditionally considered impure to carry out rituals and have a set of rules to follow.
                  Also, there was a stigma about menses among teenage girls. Thus, to reach men and women of
                  different age groups, the MHM trainer planned an interview in MHM awareness on the All India
                  Radio.



                 What was achieved?

                 Through the MHM awareness session conducted, the master trainer was successfully able to
                 reach out to a major population to curb the disbelief among them. In return, the trainer received
                 calls from friends and relatives who thanked her for resolving many of the misconceptions and
                 superstitions around menstruation they had throughout these years. They also said that as a big
                 platform like radio was chosen, menstruation was no more stigmatized like before in Dhule.
                 Who contributed?

                 The team from All India Radio was very cooperative in conducting the interview on MHM. There
                 was constant support and guidance from Ms. Smita Saraf (teacher) who boosted the MHM
                 master trainer’s confidence to speak confidently on the topic.


         Who were impacted?

          All the listeners of the All India Radio, who tunned in the channel on that day at the given time in Dhule
          were benefitted from this awareness session.




                                                                                     32]]></page><page Index="43"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra















         During the field visits in Dhule, it was observed by the MHM trainer that there were a lot of traditions and
         taboos related to menstruation among the community members. Women were isolated during menstruation
         as they were seen as unclean, dangerous, or bringing bad luck to those who encountered them. They would
         have to refrain from any religious actives and household chores during this period. Thus these women would
         opt for the hormonal pills to prepone or postpone menses according to the upcoming festivals and family
         functions. This was very hazardous for their health yet was masked due to widespread ignorance. The MHM
         master trainer took up an initiative with the guidance of Ms. Smita Saraf (teacher) to reach out to men and
         women of all age groups. They planned an awareness session on the All India Radio.

         A positive response was received from the All India Radio team. The MHM master trainer was initially
         nervous as she had never entered a radio station before. Yet she was strongly determined about the task to
         be performed. There was a lot of cooperation from the radio team. She gathered all the necessary
         information and gave an interview on All India Radio which was aired at 6 pm in Dhule. Various topics were
         covered like the mental and physical changes in boys and girls when they hit puberty, the use, and disposal
         of various menstrual hygiene products. The scientific reasons behind certain traditions practiced were
         explained and ways to curb the misconceptions were discussed. Overall the session was very impactful as
         per the feedback received from the listeners.


                                                                          Smt.Vaishali Prakash Patil
                                                                      Subject Resource Person, DIET Dhule









































                       33]]></page><page Index="44"><![CDATA[]]></page><page Index="45"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra

































         Awareness sessions




         on MHM across Maharashtra









         Menstruation and menstrual hygiene practices surrounded by taboos and socio-cultural restrictions resulted
         in women remaining ignorant of the scientific facts and hygiene practices, which in turn led to adverse
         health outcomes. School dropout rates had increased due to the lack of MHM facilities in schools. Also, the
         lack of awareness in remote parts of Maharashtra was taking a heavy toll on the health of girls and women.
         Over the years the menstruation and menstruators have been shadowed by superstitions and
         misconceptions. The only way out was to break the silence by educating both men and women about the
         physical changes experienced by women during the growth years.

         The Department of Education and Sports under the Government of Maharashtra along with UNICEF,
         Maharashtra identified menstrual hygiene management trainers to create awareness about MHM from the
         Z.P. schools in all districts across Maharashtra. Awareness sessions were conducted by MHM trainers in
         schools and public gatherings in urban and rural areas. Through these sessions need for improving MHM
         facilities was identified through discussions with parents, teachers, and community members. Initiatives like
         developing changing rooms, setting up of pad bank in schools, installing vending machines and incinerators
         were undertaken by school teachers, MHM master trainers, officials, and local leaders. Innovative ways to
         create awareness like street plays, Meena-Raju Stories, puppetry, essay writing, slogans/jingle making, and
         elocution competitions were undertaken. This helped ensure the participation of men and women from all
         age groups.
         Even during the pandemic, the awareness sessions continued through online platforms, webinars, Facebook
         lives and YouTube lives. Online sessions received enthusiastic participation from government departments,
         the private sector, and subject experts like doctors and councilors. The feedback received has encouraged
         trainers to continue their work with the same zeal even during the pandemic.



                       35]]></page><page Index="46"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra


















































                                                                                           Mumbai
















           Thane                                                                            Sangli
















           Aurangabad                                                                       Jalna


                                                                                     36]]></page><page Index="47"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra




































           Kolhapur                                                                        Jalgaon


















           Gondia                                                                      Sindhudurg














           Satara                                                                         Ratnagiri
















                       37]]></page><page Index="48"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra















         Dhule









































































                                                                                     38]]></page><page Index="49"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra















         Testimonials









                 Kum. Drishti Dattaraya Verde                           Smt. Jyoti Raut
               (Student, Patwardhan High School,              (Subject Resource Person, Dhamangaon
                           Sangli)                                         Railway)

              Madam has given us all the necessary            A large number of students, teachers and
             information about MHM. My mother had              parents of the district who participated
             told me that I have grown up, when I got         got scientific, accurate information about
              my periods. She would not allow me to            menstruation. Even during the Covid-19
               use sanitary pads nor go out to play.           pandemic, an excellent online program
             After the awareness program conducted,           was organized under the Amravati District
              I am allowed to go to school everyday.         Institute of Education and Training (DIET).
             We have pad banks in schools and so we           Thank you very much for organizing such
               don’t need to miss school during the           a commendable event under the Amravati
                           periods.                                          DIET.











                      Smt. Sunita Katam                              Kum. Monica Kachkure
                 (Post Graduate Teacher, Yavat)                 (Student, Z. P. School, Ladsavangi)

                After this awareness session, the             I avoided coming to school during periods
              feedback of the parents of the students        but because of changing room and access
                were received through WhatsApp                  to toilets. We can also get napkins in
              messages and letters. This further gave           school which is of huge help during
              us the encouragement to continue with            menstruation as we do not have to rush
             our journey of creating awareness about          home if required. With this facilites I can
                Menstrual Hygiene Management.                        attend school everyday.













                       39]]></page><page Index="50"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra















         Recognitions received









































































                                                                                     40]]></page><page Index="51"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra















         Recognitions received









































































                       41]]></page><page Index="52"><![CDATA[Success stories of menstrual hygiene management in Maharashtra




         The Changemakers]]></page><page Index="53"><![CDATA[#Period







                                a blessing not a problem]]></page></pages></Search>